<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The new Athenians no noble Bereans: being an answer to the Athenian Mercury of the 7th instant, in behalf of the people called Quakers.</title>
            <author>Penn, William, 1644-1718.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 31KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90418</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">45578401</idno>
  <idno type="VID">172323</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240913464</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1325</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R181625</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">45578401</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90418)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 172323)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2625:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The new Athenians no noble Bereans: being an answer to the Athenian Mercury of the 7th instant, in behalf of the people called Quakers.</title>
                  <author>Penn, William, 1644-1718.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([2] p.).   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Northcott in George-yard in Lonbard-street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1692.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Penn by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Friends' Library (London, England).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Society of Friends --  Apologetic works.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Oaths.</term>
               <term type="genre_form">Broadsides --  England --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Zev Berger </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:172323:1"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The New</hi> ATHENIANS <hi>no Noble</hi> BAREANS: <hi>Being an Answer to the</hi> Athenian Mercury <hi>of the 7th Instant, in behalf of the People called</hi> QUAKERS.</head>
            <p>I Am heartily sorry to see Men, professing so much Ingenuity, fall so much below their Pretensions. Your <hi>Design,</hi> at first, carried the Face of Instruction, and gave us hopes of a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Improvement of useful Learning; and for that rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son your Papers were as welcome to Us, as any other People; especially those that referred to <hi>Natural Philosophy, Mathematicks,</hi> and <hi>History:</hi> Insomuch, that some of us collected them as they came out, and others bought them as they were compleated into Volumes; being much concerned if at any time trivial or light Questions were considered, as an unworthy diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion from the end by you in the beginning proposed. But you have not only been led, upon such occasions, to exceed too often the bounds of modesty, but you have taken occasion also to vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late those of Christianity, in falling upon peoples Opinions in Religion, instead of giving your own impartially; and upon their Persons likewise, and at last the Society it self, as if your business were to expose them instead of informing them, and to increase Animosities rather than to take up their time with more peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and profitable Subjects. What if you were I ad to speak of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Principle held by the People called <hi>Quakers?</hi> Could not that have been done as indifferent persons, which you by your very Design would bespeak your selves to all Perswasions, and not as Parties Disputants and angry Antagonists? Might not the Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the People have past for good and sincere, though any part of their Doctrine had, in your opinion been unsound; but you must use hard Words and Names for both Things and Persons? A so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber and unconcerned Answer, upon any Question that might be sent you relating to their Belief, would have taken better with every body that deserved your pains, and have brought us sooner to reflect upon our mistakes, if such they were: But, in earnest, it looks as if you were almost aground, and wanted Matter, that so specious a Design as this first shewed it self, should dwindle away into Froward Controversie and Personal Invectives about Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; or that you are not sufficient fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> your Work, that can be so easily moved out of your province.</p>
            <p>I beseech you leave this preposterous Digression and pursue your own Business with more care and exactness; and before you go, suffer your selves first to be a little better informed of what you have so irregularly and undeservedly censur'd.</p>
            <p>You take occasion at these words, <hi>Truth is always persecuted,</hi> to say, <hi>that will indifferently serve</hi> Turk, Jew, Heathen, <hi>or</hi> Heretick, <hi>as well as the</hi> Quakers. This is harsh and unchristian. Are none worse than we? and we as great Hereticks as any? You judge before you convict us: 'Tis too gross partiality, and false in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry degree. But whatever the persecuted be, the <hi>Persecutor</hi> to be sure is always in the wrong; which is your case against the <hi>Quakers.</hi> But you recriminate and will prove us Persecutors. That were to the purpose indeed. Let us hear it. <hi>You excommunicate such as will not subject to your Injunctions:</hi> And good reason too, if they are Injunctions of civil order. He that joyns himself to any Society, is obliged to the Rules of that Society; and every Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty has, and must have that power upon the Members that consti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute it, or confusion follows and the Society dissolves. For in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance, Injunctions about <hi>Civil Controversies, Care of poor Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phans, due and orderly Proceedings relating to Marriages,</hi> &amp;c. are to be complied with, without the reproach of Persecution: And yet farther too; look upon what Principles of Communion any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son enters into any Society, if he leave them, or any of them, it is no Persecution to disown him in that thing wherein he alters; so that it touches not Person or Estate: for that is Persecution in a proper sense; which is not our case. But we <hi>Imprison such as di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sturb our Meetings.</hi> How this will be proved, is hard to tell; and yet if it be persecution, it will light hardest elsewhere, even upon those perhaps that you account us Hereticks for separating from. But, thanks be to God, we can and do deny the Charge. <hi>See,</hi> say you, <hi>Francis Bug's one Blow more:</hi> But if this be <hi>Athenian,</hi> it is not <hi>Barean,</hi> to condemn an whole People upon another man's au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, that you are not assured was well grounded. Besides, it is a Book we have answer'd, which you take no notice of, and that is unfair, if you knew of it; and if you did not, you ought to have asked, before you had espoused another man's Allegations. This is not answerable to that Candor you profess; and we must tell you, that <hi>Francis Bug</hi> is an <hi>Apostate Quaker,</hi> an angry, unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonable and clamorous Man; often and again detected and proved inconsistent with himself; and you will find, in the issue, of no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation to your charge against us. But did you ever read our Orders of Discipline, or have you ever been an eye or ear-wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of our Injunctions upon Conscience? if you have, you should have mentioned them, and shewn us our fault; but your evidence here, is what a discontented man says, who speaks <hi>ex parte,</hi> and is Judge in his own cause, against a Body of People he was once among, and zealous for; who, upon a private Controversie, because he had not his own will, takes pet at those that could not be brought to humour him; and from thence, run out from the very Profession of a <hi>Quaker;</hi> which shews the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation wrong, that quits a Principle for being displeased in a Man or Men. What will become of Society if such Humours are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>controulable, or they must give Rule or Law to the whole?</p>
            <p>Your next Proof of our being Persecutors, is from a passage of <hi>George Fox</hi> and <hi>George Roff,</hi> in their Letters to <hi>O. Cr.</hi> by which we perceive your new Acquaintance, and with what <hi>Tools</hi> you work, which we are sorry for, both for your sakes and theirs. But those Passages are plainly wrested by you; for they advise <hi>O. Cr.</hi> to go on in the Work he was called to; and what was that pray? Is there one word of <hi>imposing</hi> Religion upon the People of those Countries, or <hi>forcing</hi> them to abjure or renounce their own? no, not a tittle of it. Where then is the Persecution? but inas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as they were Countries that did persecute, by which means the Truth of God had not a free entrance or passage, but Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitions in Popish, and Consistories in P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>stant Governments supprest all that conformed not to their re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ive Establishments; therefore he should have made it his business <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap>en the way for a true Liberty of Conscience, that Truth might <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> under Violence, and Persecution for Conscience-sake oppress its Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessors. This is the upshot of those Passages, their very scope and tendency, as will appear to any impartial Reader, that will please to weigh them with what goes before and follows. But if you call this Persecution, to be sure it must be so to fight for Religion: And if it was unlawful for <hi>O. Cr.</hi> to fight for Liberty of Conscience, who was of a fighting Principle, what think you of punishing People because of their Conscience that would not fight with you? You are very tender of a suddain, if it may but brush at us, while you do not consider the blow you give your selves and your own friends, that have but too signally appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in that spirit and practice. The Lord inform and forgive them.</p>
            <p>You justifie calling us <hi>silly Enthusiasts,</hi> for believing <hi>it is not lawful to Swear,</hi> and say <hi>you are of the same mind, because we, without reason, by the dictates of our own fancy, which we call God's Spirit, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose the Saints practice of old, of which it was prophesied it should be used under the Gospel; was so by the Apostles and Primitive Christians, nay, by God himself, therefore the</hi> Quakers <hi>are silly Enthusiasts.</hi> Thus you.</p>
            <p>Now we think this will not prove us <hi>Enthusiasts,</hi> nor <hi>silly,</hi> for we argue from a Text, and not our own Dreams or Fancies. Had we only pretended the Authority of a private Revelation for this assertion, and that not true, then it had been <hi>Enthusiasm,</hi> and we <hi>Enthusiasts,</hi> in the worst sense: It is <hi>silly indeed</hi> to call an Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>unded upon an express Text of Scripture, either <hi>Enthu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siasm</hi> or <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>lly▪</hi> when there is not a plainer Text for one God than this of our Saviour's against swearing, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. 34. <hi>Swear not at all.</hi> But if we had overstrained it, where's the silliness of it? is it <hi>Enthusiasm,</hi> or <hi>silly,</hi> to shut out all vain swearing, by shut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting out all swearing? The advantage of that exceeds the disad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of Lying in evidence, when that Lying is made as punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able as Forswearing. What silliness or Enthusiasm is in this, pray you? <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>Holland</hi> think no such thing, that have indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged that tenderness.</p>
            <p>And if the Text be but seriously considered, the Inference we make is beyond exception. First, The tendency of that Sermon upon the Mount is to shew, that the Righteousness of the Gospel <hi>excels</hi> that of the Law; as in the case of <hi>Adultery, Divorce, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge,</hi> &amp;c. But the Law forbad false and vain swearing, therefore this must refer to that which was not forbid under the Law. This is acknowledged by many learned Men, and in particular one of our own Nation, <hi>Bishop Sanderson,</hi> in his <hi>Latin</hi> Lectures, of the Obligation of an Oath. But we for another reason, that shall anon be mentioned, think he yet narrows the extent of that E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangelical Precept, for he refers to <hi>Vows</hi> only, and not Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in any case; but we to <hi>Swearing at all.</hi> And our reasons are, <hi>First,</hi> If it had been <hi>Vows</hi> only, there had been no need of sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stituting any way of speaking in the room of it. And, <hi>Secondly,</hi> If the Text cannot therefore refer to <hi>Vows</hi> in particular, <hi>Swearing at all</hi> must be intended; or nothing is forbid, that was not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid under the Law. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Christ's prohibiting Swearing and substituting something in the room of it, and that something purely referring to the way and manner of Christians declaring the Truth, it is, to us, evident that he comprehended all Cases wherein the truth of a thing is in doubt, and consequently the end of Swearing: So says Christ, <hi>Let your</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>your Speech,</hi> or <hi>your Word, be Yea, Yea; or Nay, Nay.</hi> It is rendred <hi>Communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> by our Translations, that it might refer only to common discourse, that word being sometimes so understood; and yet <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication</hi> comprehends all acts of Justice, as well as other parts of Life: For if it comprehends Discourse in dealing, it also com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehends the Evidence of that dealing, and the Laws of just dealing; and consequently the word Communication cannot les<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sen the real force of our sense of the Text; but the words of the Text do plainly express a <hi>degree,</hi> if not a <hi>form</hi> of declaring truth, be it <hi>Yea</hi> or <hi>Nay.</hi> And since Truth-speaking takes in and relates to Controversies amongst Men, as well as other parts of Humane Converse, this <hi>Text</hi> is a <hi>Measure</hi> of Truth-speaking on all those occasions also. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Now how far Christian-men may go in declaring, the Truth, or where they are to be bounded, the <hi>Text</hi> is plain, <hi>viz.</hi> a <hi>double,</hi> but <hi>bare Averment,</hi> or <hi>Denial:</hi> Let your Word or Speech be <hi>Yea, Yea; Nay, Nay:</hi> That is, let yours Answers, when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever you are asked the truth of a matter, go no farther than a <hi>simple Affirmation</hi> or <hi>Negation,</hi> which you may double if you please. <hi>Fifthly,</hi> The reason Christ gives for bounding his Followers within <hi>Yea, Yea;</hi> and <hi>Nay, Nay;</hi> excludes all Oaths, yea, all that is more than <hi>Yea, Yea;</hi> and <hi>Nay, Nay;</hi> to wit, that <hi>they come of evil,</hi> because they proceed from distrust, infidelity and impatien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy: A simple Assertion declares truth; more, is a <hi>straining</hi> of the mind, and but to stoop to unreasonable Incredulity, which hath an evil rise. Now what is more than Yea, Yea; and Nay, Nay? why <hi>Imprecations</hi> are more an outward sign, denoting an Oath is more than <hi>Yea, Yea; and Nay, Nay;</hi> and consequently <hi>cometh of evil,</hi> because below a Christians truth and sincerity to gratifie. <hi>Sixthly,</hi> And truly the Text is so far from excluding Judicial Cases, that it serves chiefly to relate to evidence upon differences. 1. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause it is in the <hi>room</hi> of the swearing the Law allowed, which was <hi>true</hi> swearing: And, 2. Because of <hi>doubling</hi> the Assertion <hi>Yea, Yea;</hi> for a single Yea is enough for a Christian in ordinary cases. Well, but you oppose to this, the Prophesie 19 <hi>Isai. v.</hi> 18. to which, if you please, we will add two more, <hi>ch.</hi> 45. <hi>v.</hi> 23. and <hi>Jer.</hi> 4. 2. and make your best of them: For besides that it begs the Question, that the Prophets treated of Gospel-times, and not
<pb facs="tcp:172323:2"/> of some happy time before the period of their dispensation, God might speak to them in the language of their time to be inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted in a more spiritual sense; and this the place quoted by you shews: For <hi>ver.</hi> 21. mention is made of <hi>Oblation and Sacrifice,</hi> that shall be offered in that day, which in a Jewish sense is not true of Gospel-times, but in a Gospel-sense, to wit, <hi>Prayers</hi> and <hi>Praisings</hi> with <hi>heart</hi> and <hi>voice,</hi> is true. So it is in the case of <hi>Swearing,</hi> they shall swear in that day, as they sacrifice in that day; that is, a Christians Oath shall be his <hi>Solemn Word;</hi> and the difference is not greater between them, than between the Sacrifices and Obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of <hi>Beasts</hi> and <hi>Birds</hi> under the Law, and the Spiritual Sacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Oblations of the <hi>Hearts, Wills</hi> and <hi>Affections</hi> of People un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Gospel: And thus you see, that Prophesie stands you in little stead.</p>
            <p>But you object the practice of the Apostle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. 9. <hi>God is my Witness.</hi> 2 Cor. 11. 31. <hi>God knoweth I lye not.</hi> Gal. 1. 20. <hi>Before God I lye not.</hi> And you add, <hi>If these are not formal Oaths, you would fain know what are:</hi> In which, if you will not be offended, we will say as well as think, you have not been Ingenuous, to be so hard upon us, before ye had first stated and agreed with us what an Oath is; for if that be disputable, as it may be for what you have done to settle it, you argue at random. Premises must ever be agreed by Disputants, or nothing can follow clearly and satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factorily. We may say the same thing you say, without allowing it the same force and extent; nay Swear perhaps in your Opinion tho' not in our own; the same Words being an Oath and not an Oath, as they may be used and applyed in different manners. For if you should think that an Oath, which we think none, and you argue for Swearing by proofs, that for that Reason are none to us; how do you prove Swearing <hi>lawful,</hi> or convince us that not Swearing at all is <hi>Silly</hi> and <hi>Enthusiastical,</hi> when you have not yet adjusted <hi>what is Swearing at all?</hi> This had been well worth your <hi>Mercury,</hi> for it had been informing, and shewn good Reading.</p>
            <p>But you put it off thus, after citing the Apostle's words, <hi>God is my Witness,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>If these are not formal Oaths, we'd fain know what are.</hi> In which you shift your Post, and turn <hi>Querist,</hi> instead of answering Questions.</p>
            <p>But having such supposed able Men to deal with, we are not willing to be put off so; and therefore return it upon you, to state what an Oath is, which you so zealously recommend; deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, on our part, any of those Texts to be an Oath,</p>
            <p>As did <hi>Basil</hi> the Great, upon <hi>Psalm</hi> 15. And <hi>Gregory Nazianzen,</hi> in his Dialogue against <hi>Swearing:</hi> And Bishop <hi>Sanderson</hi> in his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of <hi>Joseph,</hi> in his <hi>Oxford</hi> Lectures; which will much better defend the Apostle from your Imputation.</p>
            <p>For what you say of <hi>Tertullian,</hi> you wrong him extreamly, and your Reader also, by not telling him where to find it: For in his Apology, <hi>Chap.</hi> 32. whence, we suppose, your Objection is taken, he does equivocally and improperly own Swearing, <hi>That they Swore, tho' not by the Genius of</hi> Caesar, <hi>yet for the health and safety of</hi> Caesar, just as they did Sacrifice. <hi>Hoc salvum esse volumus, &amp; pro magno id juramento habemus.</hi>
               <q>Our wishing well to <hi>Caesar</hi> we have or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count for an Oath, or instead of an Oath.</q> And as the <hi>Pythago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians</hi> say, <hi>There is in all reasonable Creatures an Oath or Tye,</hi> viz. <hi>A Mind, not to transgress the Law of God:</hi> And as <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus</hi> speaks, <hi>That a good Man Swears by his Deeds.</hi> So <hi>Tertullian</hi> urged upon them, That the Christians sacrificed <hi>for the health of</hi> Caesar, as well as they, but it was in the Christian way, by <hi>pure Prayers.</hi> So that as he was for <hi>Sacrifice,</hi> he was for <hi>Swearing.</hi> Thus to <hi>Scapula.</hi> C. 1, 2.</p>
            <p>And in his Book of Idolatry, <hi>Chap.</hi> 11. <q>I speak not of Perjury, says he, because it is not lawful to Swear. And <hi>Chap.</hi> 31. He that signs a Bill of Security, containing an Oath, is guilty of Swearing, and transgresses Christ's Command, who hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded not to Swear.</q> And speaking of the Temptations Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians were exposed to, if they should lanch into the Traffick of the World, he adds, <hi>Not to speak of Forswearing, seeing it is not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, so much as to Swear.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We are the longer upon this, because he is one of your Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities. Your other is <hi>Athanasius, That he purged himself by an Oath, pleading the Apostle's example.</hi> Which, by the way, looks like an Excuse for doing it, and as if in other cases he did not allow it. But pray take the pains to read his Annotations upon <hi>Christ's Passion,</hi> and you will find, first, That he denies all Swearing; and upon our Grounds. <q>The Evangelical Sentence, says he, of the Lord is, Let your Yea be Yea, and your Nay,</q> Nay: Thus far we, who are in Christ, may confirm our Words with Asseverati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, but come no nearer to an Oath.</p>
            <p>To this he objects himself, the common Opinion, <hi>That God Swore.</hi> He answers it, <q>That God did not properly and formally Swear, nor could not; for the nature of an Oath is to Swear by that which is greater and better than ones self, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. 16. But if any thing, says he, this must be said, His word is an Oath to Man for Verity, because of his Faithfulness and Truth.</q> And he will not have the Apostle to have Sworn, nor the most ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrated Fathers of and before his time. So that we return it up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you, that if at any time they used those Expressions of the Apostle, it was in Church Matters, and because they did not think it an Oath. And if you will please to turn to <hi>Just. Martyr</hi>'s se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Apology, <hi>p.</hi> 63. you will find he is of the same Mind; <hi>We should speak, but not sware the Truth,</hi> and vouches Christ's Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5, for it. <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus,</hi> lib. 7. and <hi>Tertullian</hi>'s Contemporary, <hi>Cyprian, Hillary, Grig. Nyssen, Caesarius, Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanius, Ambrose,</hi> and <hi>Chrysostome</hi> above all the rest, styled the <hi>Golden Doctor</hi> or Father, out of whose Discourse, upon this Subject, we observe these 5 Things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>That Oaths are not lawful under the Gospel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>The Reason of it, that their Evangelical Verity is the Christian, and a better Security.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>That the rise of an Oath is Infidelity and Distrust, which are from Evil, and that is below a Christian state; for he that dare not Swear, which once was permitted, dare not Lye, which never was permitted; and therefore his Yea, is Yea, and his Nay, Nay.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>That Swearing was a Condescention to a weak and low state of the World, to divert People from Swearing by false Gods, which was the evil custom of those times;</hi> as if God should say, I will suffer you to Swear, if you will Swear by me that am the true God, and not by their false Gods: And that from hence came his Command to Swear by him, not for the sake of Swearing, but to avoid Idolatry.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>That this Principle is the only means of rooting out all evil Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of the World.</hi> Take the Cure for this most Pernicious and Epidemical Distemper, in the words of <hi>Basil</hi> the great.</p>
            <p>
               <q>The Remedy consisteth in a twofold Admonition, First, not to Swear at all: Secondly, to suppress the Form of Oaths.</q> I will close with what the In<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>titu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons say, that go under the name of <hi>Clemens Romanus.</hi>
               <q>Our Master hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded that we should not Swear, <hi>no not by the true God;</hi>
               </q> but that our Word should be more credible than an Oath. This <hi>Clemens</hi> was very ancient, you know, since the Apostle <hi>Paul</hi> mentions him, and that to him some of the Ancients ascribe the Epistle to the <hi>Hebrews.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We hope, after you have considered the Authorities that support this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrin, you will be so charitable at least to allow that we are neither <hi>Silly</hi> nor <hi>Enthusiasts</hi> for asserting it. This comprehending your Answers and Excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to the Queries upon this Subject (for against a Command so p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ainly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, they must fall of course) we are under no Obligation to consider them, and yet they sall not pass our notice, tho it were but to let you see how little they deserve it.</p>
            <p>The first Query is, <q>If Christ's coming did not supersede Oaths, since it was to end Sin, the occasion of Oaths? The second, If Man improving the means given him to answer that end, may not obtain it?</q> I put them together because you give the same Answer to both, which is Negative; and for the same Reason, <hi>viz.</hi>
               <q>Because Christ did not come to end Sin: And your Reason</q> for that is. <q>;That if Christ intended to have ended Sin by his coming, it had been ended, which is not so, and therefore it was not the end of his coming.</q> This opposes as plain a Text as is in the Bible, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. 5, 6. <hi>And ye know he was manifest to take away our Sins. Whosoever abideth in him sinneth not; Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever is born of God doth not commit Sin.</hi> The Angel thus declared the end of his coming, <hi>Mat.</hi> 1. 21. Christ commands Perfection, <hi>Chap.</hi> 5. 48. <hi>Be ye perfect as your heavenly Father is perfect.</hi> The Heavenly Leaven was given to Leaven the whole Lump, <hi>Chap.</hi> 13. 33. The Apostle desired, That the Christians of his time might be sanctified throughout in Body, Soul and Spirit; which leaves out no part of Man, nor no part of that part unsanctified, 1 <hi>Thes</hi> 5. 23. and exhorted them to press forward to the Mark which was a Perfect Man, even to the measure of the fulness of Christ. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 14, 15. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 13. In which Passages the end of Christ's coming, and the work and blessing of the Gospel, <hi>was to end Sin,</hi> both as to the <hi>Guilt</hi> and <hi>Nature</hi> of it: and to <hi>sanctify</hi> and <hi>regenerate</hi> the Soul. Read <hi>Phil.</hi> 1. 10. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 11. <hi>Tit.</hi> 3. 5. <hi>Heb.</hi> 2. 11.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Your Reason is both weak and dangerous: For if all comes to pass that Christ intends, then he intended not the conversion of <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing he lamented it so, because it came not to pass. Again, if Christ in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to take away the Guilt and Power of Sin, it should accordingly be taken away: but in whole Nations of Believers, how very few can say it, or can you say it of? Nor know you but that there are some that walk <hi>blamelesly</hi> now as well as then. Your Ignorance is no Argument to the contrary: A Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple may be true for all Mens Practices, and Gods end for good to Man, tho Man may frustrate it to himself.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Scriptures you urge are against you, <hi>Jam.</hi> 3. 2. Here we will joyn issue with you, his Chapter being a strong proof of our Point; yea this very verse: For it supposes a <hi>perfect Man,</hi> which you deny, and by the similies of a <hi>Bridle</hi> and an <hi>Helm,</hi> it shews how a Man may come to be so. But, say you, in the name of the Apostle, <hi>In many things we offend all:</hi> Yet consid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r, pray, that the Apostle included himself no more there than verse 9. where speaking of the Tongue, he also saith, <hi>Tberewith bless we God, and therewith curse we Men.</hi> You cannot therefore think, I hope, that the Apostle was a <hi>Curs<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r;</hi> but it was a way of speaking to fetch in the Guilty, and the better to reach them, by personating them or involving himself among them.</p>
            <p>Hear again the same Apostle in this very Chapter, vers. 11. 12. <hi>Doth a F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>untain send forth at the same place sweet Water and bitter? Can the Fig-Tree, my bretbren, bear Olives?</hi> Yes say the <hi>Athenians,</hi> no say the <hi>Quakers.</hi> Pray who keeps closest to the Text? Hear him further, vers. 17. and ch. 1. 27. he tells you the nature and end of their Religion. In few words, <hi>Humani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> and <hi>Purity, Bowels</hi> and <hi>Holiness,</hi> they are the pure Religion and <hi>undefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led</hi> in God's sight, in his account; not <hi>Creeds</hi> but <hi>Practice,</hi> not <hi>Profession,</hi> tho of true Words, but <hi>Experience</hi> and <hi>good Living.</hi> And, without offence, had you been of this Religion, you would have been less exceptions at us and ours. Your next Scripture is as unhappily chosen as the former, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1. 8. <hi>If that we say we have no Sin we deceive our selves and the Truth is not in us.</hi> Now if you please but to read the verse foregoing and following, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps you will see it is not to your purpose.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If we walk in the light as (God) is in the Light, we have Fellowship one with another, and the Blood of Jesus Christ his Son cleanseth us from all Sin.</hi> Now follows your Text; <hi>If we say we have no Sin</hi> (that is, no Sin to be cleansed from, no need of Christ to take away our Sins) <hi>we deceive our selves and the Truth is not in us.</hi> Observe now what follows, we desire you. <hi>If we confess our Sins, he is faithful and just to forgive us our Sins) and to cleanse us from all unrighteousness;</hi> which comprehends both the <hi>Guilt</hi> and <hi>Nature</hi> of Sin. And that we have not misinterpreted your Text, the next and last verse proves our Sense genuine; <hi>If we say that we have not sinned we make him a Lyer, and his word is not in us:</hi> That is, if we say we have not sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and so have no need of a propitiation for Sins past, or to be cleansed from the Sin that is present, we make God a Lyer, that says we are Sinners, and therefore sent us his Son to redeem us from Sin. But now we will sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose your Answers good to the two Queries; pray what does that lessen the validity of <hi>not Swearing at all?</hi> Tho' Men art not in all things perfect, may they not tell Truth and be believed without the <hi>force</hi> and <hi>strain</hi> af an Oath? Must all Men be Lyers that are not sinless? Look about you <hi>Athenians:</hi> If this be not the case, <hi>Swear not at all,</hi> is both good Doctrin and practicable, for all that you have said to the contrary.</p>
            <p>Your Answer to the third Query, <hi>If there be a plainer Precept than this of Swear not at all,</hi> is a <hi>Jest</hi> at us, but it turns in earnest upon your selves. <hi>Show us,</hi> say you, <hi>a more positive Command than that, He that hath two Coats let him impart to him that has none, which if we followed in Winter time,</hi> you say, <hi>we should look wors<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> than we do.</hi> But we tell you it is to be followed both <hi>Winter</hi> and <hi>Summer</hi> by all that will follow Christ; and however ill they look for it here to Scoffers, Christ will look very well upon them for it another day. But you think you pinch us by urging the Text upon us litterally, which alas is your Mistake; for so that we do not <hi>Swear,</hi> we answer that Precept tho' by other words than <hi>Yea</hi> and <hi>Nay;</hi> and if we give of our abundance to them that want, we answer this, tho not exactly in a literal sense: And now you see your <hi>Jest</hi> upon the Looks of the <hi>Quakers</hi> makes you look no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than you should do. And thus much for your first Paper; what remains being but Heads insisted upon in your following Mercuries, where I shall find them, and in my next consider them particularly as they lie.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>LONDON: <hi>Printed for</hi> Thomas Northcott <hi>in</hi> George-vard <hi>in</hi> Lombard-street 16<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>2.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>